And now the דף, daf, we're wrapping up the whole issue around
the amount of money for the פדיון הבן pidyon haben and we
are three, two lines from the top, שלושים של עבד וחמישים של
אונס ושל מפתה. shelosheem shel eved ve'chamishim shel ones ve'shel mepateh. So
we have just said that when the תורה Torah speaks about שקל
shekel or כסף kessef and a specific amount, not a generic כסף
kessef as in money, but a specific amount, it's referring to שקל
הקודש, shekel hakodesh, it's referring to which is a silver שקל shekel
which is same as this מנה צורי, manah tzuri, which is this
whole ratio on the board which now Bobby has just provided us
with a nice sheet which is four דינר dinar which is four
זוז zuz and eventually becomes 768 פרוטות. prutas. So that is the
type of שקל shekel that we're talking about when the תורה Torah
refers to שקל. shekel. And the משנה mishnah and then the גמרא
gemara added that when they use a phrase סלע sela in rabbinic
amounts, we're referring actually to a סלע מדינה sela medina which is
one eighth.
So now the גמרא gemara continues and says the following on the
משנה mishnah that says the thirty of the עבד eved that the
תורה Torah says or the fifty of when there's a case of
אונס ones and seduction, it's referring to the שקל. shekel. I should
again say what we said yesterday that the fifty of the אונס
ones and the seduction, because the תורה Torah calls it כמוהר הבתולות,
kemo mohar habetulot, like the מוהר mohar that is paid for virgins,
and fifty שקל shekel is, a שקל shekel is four זוז, zuz,
is 200 זוז, zuz, that gives us the amount of the כתובה
kethubah price which is the 200 זוז zuz for a בתולה. betulah.
Anyway, let's see what the גמרא gemara says. הא תו למה
לי, ha tu lamma lee, why do I need anything, why do
I need to list all of the cases in the משנה? mishnah?
Once התנא ליה רישא, hatanna lei risha, the beginning said that every
time it refers to כסף kessef in the תורה Torah it's מנה
צורי, manah tzuri, why did it have to give me these specific
examples? So the גמרא gemara says, אונס ומוציא שם רע אצטריכא ליה.
ones umotzi shem ra itztrecha leh. No, you needed it for the
case of the rapist and the case of the person that libels,
no that's not a better word than libel, what is it? Libel?
Anyway, his wife, defames his wife. Defames his wife. Anyway, so there
the תורה Torah does not explicitly use the word שקל. shekel. It
uses the word כסף, kessef, but it does not use the word
שקל shekel and therefore it has to tell me that כסף kessef
means שקל. shekel. So we know שקל shekel means the מנה צורי
manah tzuri coinage, but what we don't know is that the word
כסף kessef when it's with a specific amount also means שקל. shekel.
So the גמרא gemara says, סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka da'atach amina, I
would have thought, כיון דלא כתיב בהו שקלים, keivan dela ktiv behu
shekalim,
it doesn't say שקל, shekel, it just says כסף. kessef. רש״י Rashi
quotes the פסוק, pasuk, it says, it says, no he doesn't quote
the פסוק pasuk there, by מוציא שם רע motzi shem ra it
says, יענשו אותו מאה כסף, ya'anshu oto me'ah kessef,
they shall punish him with 100 כסף, kessef, okay,
or חמישים כסף chamishim kessef it says by the case of the
אונס. ones. So it says 50 or 100 כסף, kessef, but it
does not say שקל. shekel. So I would have thought דבכל דהו
בעלמא, debechol dahu be'almah, so maybe it's some lesser כסף kessef silver
coin. קמשמע לן דמילף כסף כסף מהדדי, k'mashma lan demilef kessef kessef
mehadadi, you learn now כסף כסף kessef kessef and since by some
of them it says שקל, shekel, we assume by all of them
it's שקל. shekel. So this is the basic principle that when the
תורה Torah gives a fixed amount of silver, it's referring to silver
שקלים shekalim and שקל shekel is the מנה צורי, manah tzuri, which
is the whole equation we did on the board with again Bobby
just gave us this nice thing here today, which was the chart
I was trying to do on the board, but it's very clear
here. So one סלע sela or one שקל, shekel, right, is four
זוז, zuz, is then 24 all the way down to 768 פרוטות
prutas and that is what the תורה Torah refers to when it
says שקל shekel and again or סלע. sela. When we refer to
the תורה Torah as סלע, sela, when the גמרא gemara refers to
rabbinic obligations of סלע, sela, that refers to a, that is one
eighth of that, which as I said leads to some discussion
by כתובה kethubah whether referring to the biblical or to the rabbinic.
But as we pointed out, even if we're referring to the biblical,
50, 50 שקל, shekel, 200 זוז, zuz, times 50 שקל, shekel, which
is the amount in the תורה, Torah, is ten times בכור, bechor,
and בכור bechor we said is roughly, I don't know, between 75
and 125 dollars based on the price of silver. So really the
amount of the כתובה kethubah if you say about 100, so ten
times 100 is really only a thousand dollars, which isn't much. So
as we mentioned yesterday, that's why in the Middle Ages they added
the תוספת כתובה tosefet kethubah and the fixed amount, the find of
the dowry at 100 זקוק zakuk each, and a זקוק zakuk is
a lot more than a זוז, zuz, and the 200 זקוקים zakukim
which we refer to is where the real value of the כתובה
kethubah lies. Yes, Charlie.
That actually might have been a large amount in המשנה Mishnaic times,
because
we don't have a concept of how poor the world was. Right,
right.
Just, right. I mean
the amount of the כתובה kethubah was supposed to be sufficient to
support somebody for a year, a person or maybe even two people
for a year. Okay, so certainly a thousand dollars wouldn't have done
it. Right? I mean what's the poverty line right now, you know,
I don't know, what, 25,000 or something, what is that for a
family of two or for what?
Anyway, it's ten, it's ten... is in the five figures.
Right, right, absolutely. But that's why they, you know, in the Middle
Ages, they added, they created this addition to the כתובה ketubah in
order to get it to be something reasonable. All right, so let's
finish this up. חוץ מן השקלים. Chutz min hashkalim. Now the one
exception, now this is on the part of the משנה Mishnah that
says in all these things you can use שווה כסף, shaveh kessef,
it doesn't actually have to be silver coins or coinage altogether, it
can even be any any property of value. So you can... we're
going to talk about that like you could give for, you know,
for your בכור, bechor, you could give for your פדיון הבן, pidyon
haben, you could give a כהן kohen your DVD, you could give
your flat screen TV, although that would be a little bit excessive.
But anyway, so it could be שווה כסף. shaveh kessef. It says
with the exception of שקלים. shkalim. So, which means when you give
a שקל shekel in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, you give the
half a שקל shekel each year, that has to be actual coins
and it cannot be equivalencies. Let's take a look why. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this.
I have a question with this thing about the money supporting a
woman for a year. If the woman has four children from this
husband, presumably does the... do the children stay with the woman? And
does that money include support for the woman and her children?
So that's a good question. So basically according... for the most part
according to the גמרא, Gemara, I mean that's a whole separate question
about who has custody. The גמרא Gemara generally assumes, because it generally
assumes, you know, for so much of the family structure that it's
defined by the man, that the children stay with the husband, with
the father. That being said, it does say that when the children
are very young, that then for the benefit of the children they,
you know, they're with the mother. But that's only during their sort
of young years. As sort of Rivka was pointing
out, תקנה, takanah, boys go to the father according to the גמרא.
Gemara. Right, in contemporary בית דין, beis din, as Rivka was saying
in general, as we were talking before the שיעור shiur about how
much things have sort of adapted to larger contemporary realities, if, you
know, at least in theory if a case were brought... I don't
know how they actually operate, but from what I've been told is
that if cases of custody are brought in front of a בית
דין, beis din, they try to make the decision, well at least
the בית Beis of America says that they make the decision on
the best interest of the child. I don't know if that actually
is borne out in fact. But in the גמרא, Gemara, otherwise, yeah,
under six they're with the mother, over six they're with the father
because basically it's assumed a male head of household family structure. Yeah.
So but I'm just wondering though, does the mother...
no the money does not include the support of the kids.
Yeah. But a man has an obligation
once they're age six.
Right. Right, but the father is obligated in support, right, the father
is obligated to support the kids. But the amount that goes to
the mother in the case of כתובה ketubah and divorce does not
include child support, but he has a separate obligation of child support.
But it is, as Rivka says, limited to a very young age.
Afterwards, you know, they're out, or they go out and they apprentice
themselves or whatever. Yeah.
Poverty level for a family of four is twenty-two thousand three-fifty.
Okay, so it's about six, well I guess there's economy of scale,
but it's about six thousand per person. Okay, something like that. Probably
say around ten thousand. All right, so let's finish now...
yes, ten thousand eight-ninety for one person.
Ten thousand eight-ninety for a person. Okay. So let's take a look
now at the at the wrapping up of this משנה. Mishnah. חוץ
מן השקלים. Chutz min hashkalim. תנא: Tana: חוץ מן השקלים ומעשר ודהראיון.
chutz min hashkalim u'ma'aser v'deharayon. It says with the exception about things
that cannot just be שווה כסף shaveh kessef is the שקל shekel
that is sent to the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, a half שקל
shekel each year, מעשר, ma'aser, which is your מעשר שני, ma'aser sheni,
you redeem your מעשר שני ma'aser sheni on money and you bring
it to the to the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, and ראיון, ra'ayon,
which is עולת ראיה, olas re'iyah, when every... for the רגלים regalim
it says יראה כל זכורך, yeira'eh kol zechurcha, you have to appear
and you have to bring a קרבן. korban. So now we're talking
about the money that you bring in order to pay for the
קרבן. korban. So let's take a look at these three. שקלים דתנן,
Shkalim detnan, why money you
bring for other קרבנות korbanos doesn't need to be שקלים? shkalim?
Well, yeah, you buy your קרבן korban with whatever you buy it
with, you
know, you can give a part.
Well we'll talk about that, it's a good question. Let's take a
look. שקלים, Shkalim, so צד תנן: tzad tnan: מצרפים שקלים, metzarfin shkalim,
now our word here is לדרבונות. ledarbonos. א דרבן A darban is
actually like a type of a thing that is used to to,
you know, to whip, not to whip or whatever, to prod a
a goat, you know, חמור, chamor, exactly, exactly, an animal. What does
that have to do here? Here it obviously means some type of
a coin, some larger coin. If you look at the side, it
says that the גירסא girsa in the משנה Mishnah is לדרכונות, ledarkonos,
a דראכמה, drachma, right, is an ancient Roman coin. Is it that,
a דראכמה? drachma? Greek coin. Anyway, so it probably means דראכמות drachmas
or something like that. Anyway, you can you can combine them to
larger coins. So if you redeemed your מעשר ma'aser on small coins,
on שקלים, shkalim, which as we've been learning are not so small,
you can then exchange your שקלים shkalim or transfer it to larger
coins, מפני משא הדרך, mipnei masa haderech, because of the schlepping on
the way, and you don't want to have to, you know, you
don't want to bring a bag full of pennies, as it were.
We're not talking about pennies, but whatever, you want to bring larger
currencies, larger denominations. Now what does that prove in terms of this
issue? So רש״י Rashi says here, one minute. So
if
you look at רש"י Rashi *Rashi* it's interesting because the real point
is not in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* but the real point is
in רש"י Rashi *Rashi* brings down the real דרשה drasha *drasha*. It's
like three lines below the line of הגוסטא *Hagusta* where it says
מעשר שני ma'aser sheni *Maaser Sheni*. רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says אינו נפדה
אלא בכסף טבוע *eino nifdeh ela bekesef tavua*, only by minted coins,
ולא בשוה כסף kesef *velo beshaveh kesef*, ואפילו פרוטות דנחשא שפיר דמי
*ve'afillu prutos dechosha shapir dami*, even if it's like not silver, even
if it's copper, it's okay, but it has to be minted coins.
And then later he says and this reason
and then he says at the bottom, right near the משנה mishnah:
*Mishna*, he says ובמסכת שקלים shkalim פירש טעמא שמא תיזול מרגליות. הוא
הדין לחוש שוה כסף shaveh kesef שמא תיזול ונמצא הקדש מפסיד *uvemaseches
Shekalim piresh ta'ama shema tizu margaliyot. Hu din lachosh shaveh kesef shema
yizol venimtza hekdesh mafsid*. So he says what's the reason? It's not
here, it's not even in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. The גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* just talks about a case of one minute about redeeming it
with coins. But there's two הלכות *halachos* by מעשר שני ma'aser sheni
*Maaser Sheni*, okay? The first הלכה halacha *halacha* by מעשר שני Ma'aser
Sheni *Maaser Sheni* is וצרת הכסף בידך Vetzarta hakesef beyadecha *vetzarta hakesef
beyadecha*, which is from there we learn literally means you bind the
money in your hands, but the דרשה drasha *drasha* is that it
has to be on כסף צורה kesef tzurah *kesef tzurah*, on minted
coins. So the original redemption of מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni *Maaser Sheni*
has to be on minted coins, okay? But it could be any
coin, it could even be copper פרוטות *prutos*, pennies. Now, now that
I've already redeemed it, why can't I transfer that
קדושה kedusha. *kedusha* to let's say a diamond or a pearl? Why
can I only transfer it to a דרכמה *drachma* or a gold
coin? But why does it have to keep it as coins? So
this is a different reason. After the initial redemption was done on
coins, the reason now I have to keep it as coins is
a concern about devaluation. That if I transfer it to pearls or
to diamonds or whatever it is, maybe by the time I get
to ירושלים Yerushalayim? *Yerushalayim* those things will be worth less than they
were initially worth. Now of course we know that yes, but if
your standard of measurement is dollars, then it can't be worth less
dollars. Now of course it's all relative, I
understand. I understand it's all relative, right? Yes, if you transfer it
to a thousand דרכמה *drachma*, when you get ירושלים *Yerushalayim* it'll still
be worth a thousand דרכמה *drachma*. Now a thousand דרכמה *drachma* might
buy a lot less bread than it could have bought a while
ago, that is all true. But somehow if conceptually we're thinking in
dollars or in דרכמה *drachma*, we say this doesn't get devalued. Other
things might be devalued. That's the mindset, but I do maybe there's
also a economic reality that
because price of certain goods might fluctuate vis-a-vis money but price of
other goods, some goods might become more expensive but other goods might
be cheaper vis-a-vis money. So anyway that is the reason is because
of concern
about devaluation. Yes.
Yeah, I brought this up to you before that this actually does
appear in other גמרות *Gemaros*, the this דרשה drasha. *drasha* you just
mentioned. Right. And my problem was
that alright,
even in the time of the תורה Torah *Torah* there wasn't coins?
I know you said in
the time of אברהם *Avraham*.
There were no coins. Is that really true? No coins. Coins are
ubiquitous in archaeological sites. Yes. And there are no coins that are
older than about twenty-six hundred years old. Really? They've never found a
coin older than that.
Wow. Alright. So anyway all I can tell you
is that to say in general, in general the fact that a
דרשה drasha. *drasha* does not work with the time of the תורה
Torah *Torah*, even if it's explaining a דאורייתא *d'oraisa*, is not I
think itself a problem because the רמב"ם *Rambam* already says that the
nature of תורה שבעל פה Torah SheBe'al Peh. *Torah Shebe'al Peh*, if
you don't assume that this is הלכה halacha למשה מסיני *Halacha L'Moshe
MiSinai*, right, straight given by God at סיני *Sinai*. If you assume
that this is a דרשה drasha. *drasha* learned from the פסוקים pesukim
*pesukim* and it's תורה שבעל פה Torah SheBe'al Peh *Torah Shebe'al Peh*,
the רמב"ם *Rambam* basically says, and it sounds that way from גמרות
*Gemaros*, that that can be different every בית דין *Beis Din* in
its period. It says על פי התורה... אל השופט אשר יהיה בימים
ההם, אל כל דיין שבימיך *al pi hatorah... el hashofet asher yihiye
beyamim haheim, al kol dayan shebeyamecha* refers to דרשות drashot *drashos* of
תורה Torah שבעל פה *Torah Shebe'al Peh*. And therefore it's not based
on the fact that we are discovering
what God originally meant when the תורה Torah *Torah* was given, but
that the בית דין *Beis Din* is authorized to interpret it and
what their interpretation is is the binding interpretation. So even if what
you're saying is correct, it doesn't bother me. So fine.
So before the תנאים Tannaim *Tannaim* came around that פסוק pasuk *pasuk*
was interpreted differently, once the תנאים *Tannaim* came around they interpreted it
that way. Even if historically it couldn't have been what God meant
at הר סיני *Har Sinai*, but nevertheless that becomes the binding interpretation.
So I don't really find... And you're the first person who's ever
given me a
decent
answer. Okay. But that is based on the assumption number one that
the interpretation of פסוקים psukim, *pesukim* can change over time and it's
binding, which is what the רמב"ם *Rambam* says. And number two that
it's not that the nature of תורה שבעל פה *Torah Shebe'al Peh*
is not because it was what God originally meant, but it's because...
It doesn't have to be, we hope it's close to that, but
it's because בית דין has been authorized to interpret it, which is
what the רמב"ן Ramban says on the מצוה mitzvah of לא תסור
ימין ושמאל. Lo Tasur Yamin U'smol. He says any written text can
be interpreted in many ways and God says that this תורה will
be binding according to the interpretation that חז"ל Chazal say and they're
empowered to interpret it and it's they might have to try to
attempt to understand the original meaning that's for the integrity of the
process but it doesn't mean that it doesn't mean that it has
to be right and that's I think the general answer well it
is the same תורה but its meaning is not the same and
the ר"ן Ran says the same thing I think in general that's
the most that's the best answer to challenges of archaeology and history
in terms of תורה שבעל פה.
So you mean that you're trying to say that so God's you're
saying that God meant to say like you know use coins but
the way they got to that analysis is through a potentially faulty
interpretation of פסוק pasuk but it isn't a problem because they're entitled
to interpret פסוקים psukim whichever way to get so you're saying that
the
same constitutional question no no I didn't necessarily say that it's the
same constitutional question is an is the Supreme Court's interpretation of the
Constitution binding because it was the original intent of the founding fathers
or is it binding because they've been authorized to give the binding
interpretation and the answer is B now in their process of trying
to interpret it are they supposed to attempt to understand the intent
of the founding fathers that's a different מחלוקת machlokes so that could
be also a question God here as well but that is enough
digression for now okay I know it's all much more interesting than
the שקלים shkalim but let's go on okay so that's why the
שקלים shkalim okay that it has to be money so because of
a concern of devaluation not even mentioned in the גמרא Gemara, רש"י
brings it in מאי והראיון mai ve'hara'ayon
so that's why מעשר ma'aser שקלים shkalim מעשר דכתיב ma'aser dechsiv oh
וצרת הכסף בידך Vetzarta hakesef beyadecha I'm sorry I
I conflated two things okay I apologize שקלים shkalim I'm sorry okay
I I was already jumping ahead and doing the מעשר ma'aser case
שקלים shkalim the reason is there's no there's no הלכה halacha, of
וצרת הכסף Vetzarta hakesef שקלים shkalim is just the idea of a
half שקל shekel each year for the קרבנות korbanos that is only
I apologize strike half what I said before not the part about
the תורה שבעל פה anyway so the שקלים shkalim. is all about
is all about what you know if it's just giving money for
the support of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash for the קרבנות korbanos
there there's no idea of coinage at all there there's just the
idea of that you don't want it devalued and that's why you
keep it as cash and you don't do it in other objects
that's the first point מצרפין שקלים לדרכמונות metzarfin shkalim ledarchmonos that you
do it to drachmas not other things you don't want it devalued
that's number one מעשר דכתיב ma'aser dechsiv וצרת הכסף vatzarta hakesef, בידך
that's what I was saying before that's the דרשה drasha, and that's
what Charlie was responding to of כסף kesef צורה tzurah that וצרת
Vetzarta is understood to be certainly anyway not פשט pshat in the
פסוק pasuk a coinage that has a that has a form that
has a צורה tzurah, that has an imprint on it and therefore
an image on it and therefore it has to be on it
has to be on what do you call it on on coinage
now on coin on coins now why can't you transfer to something
else because תורה then says you have I'm sorry I was conflating
it before because the תורה then says what do you use the
money for בכל אשר תאוה נפשך בבקר ובצאן bechol asher te'aveh nafshecha
babakar uvatzon etc. they have to be use it for foodstuffs so
obviously you can't now if you and so you can use it
for foodstuffs but you can't transfer to other types of goods basic
silver metal you know diamonds and so on pearls you can't do
that because once you've done the original redemption onto the money with
the coin the coinage you can only then use that to buy
food that you're going to eat as מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni okay
so that's why מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni. cannot be שוה כסף shaveh
kesef והראיון
תני רבי יוסי ve'hara'ayon tani Rabbi Yose שלא יביא סיגא לעזרה shelo
yavi siga la'azarah so why is the ראיון ra'ayon the money you
bring for the עולת ראיה olas re'iyah why does that have to
be cannot be שוה כסף shaveh kesef why does it have to
be coinage so רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose said that you should not
bring dross metal into the עזרה azarah okay because you are if
you're going to bring like שוה כסף shaveh kesef, you're going to
show up it's the רגל regel it's time to buy your עולת
ראיה olas re'iyah so you're going to say here here's my like
used VCR I want to buy my עולת ראיה olas re'iyah with
it or here's my you know here's some base you know here's
just some copper some unminted copper and that's inappropriate now of course
the עזרה azarah might be a little bit of an exaggeration because
presumably you're not buying your קרבנות korbanos in the עזרה azarah but
you might be buying them on you know if you ever walk
where in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael you know in they what they've
uncovered they had all those shops right right around at the you
know at the base of הר הבית Har HaBayis or your way
up you know what do you think people are selling on your
way up to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash they're selling sheep and
wine and oil and all that stuff so when you want when
you're going to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash in the immediate environs
do you want a whole bartering going on or do you want
people to have like basic cash and it's a simple price and
it's a much more מסודר mesudar exchange than if people were coming
and they were bringing all their junk and it was becoming a
major like bartering bazaar so that is the reason now why דווקא
davka the עולת ראיה olas re'iyah I assume because there you have
every male Jew coming right before the רגל regel so it's going
to turn the whole thing into a בלגן balagan if Coming with
my private קרבן korban and I—I'm coming with my private קרבן korban
and I want to say to this guy and make a side
deal and I say, "I've got this nice like iPhone or whatever,
you know, would you exchange that? That maybe is
okay, but that's in the middle of the week, on an individual
basis. But at the time of the
רגל, regel, קרבן פסח korban pesach too, and it's not saying it's
a problem."
That's a good question. Yeah, okay, I don't know why it wasn't
also raised in terms
of the קרבן פסח korban pesach issue, maybe אי נמי, ina nami,
good point.
Yes, מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni be eaten in ירושלים? Yes. Okay, so
it still has קדושה. kedusha It might be another reason to not
transfer the קדושה kedusha. to something
else because the money still has קדושה.
kedusha No, it doesn't work like—it doesn't—that's only שמיטה. shmita. Only שמיטה
shmita when you try to transfer does it stay on the original
thing. By מעשר ma'aser שני the value does transfer to the next
object.
Okay,
but so—but still, can you change from one coin to another coin?
No, you can't.
That's what—the first time you change—the Torah allows you to take the
קדושה kedusha from the מעשר שני and transfer it to coins. Once
you've transferred it to coins, right, I was saying it wrong before,
I was conflating the two cases of מעשר and שקלים. shkalim Once
you've transferred it to the coins, you can only then use the
coins, it says ונתתה הכסף בכל אשר תאוה נפשך בבקר ובצאן. venatata
hakesef bechol asher ta'aveh nafshecha babakar uvatzon. You can only use the
coins to buy the food that you're then going to eat for
מעשר שני.
Has to use more valuable coins though.
Well,
yes, but the other point—but the point is that in principle you
can't even begin to transfer it on. Now again, so there's three
things you can't use שוה כסף, shaveh kesef: oh my God, it's
already 8:00, there's three things, I'm going to be super fast, three
things you can't use שוה כסף: shaveh kesef one is שקלים where
although that's really just about sending a check to the בית המקדש,
Beit HaMikdash, you don't want to sort of
do it in שוה כסף kesef. because of devaluation, because it takes
time to collect all the money and to bring it to the
בית המקדש; Beit HaMikdash; מעשר שני which the Torah says וצרת הכסף,
which is Charlie's question about coinage, but regardless, there is the דרשה
drasha. by חזל Chazal is that it has to be coins, צורה,
and that once it's in the coins it can't be transferred except
for the food you're actually going to eat; and finally the issue
of ראיון ra'ayon where everybody is coming to bring an עולת ראיה
olat re'iyah and we don't want them bringing their various junk, we
want them to bring money or beasts from the field.
Sure.
Okay, let's now go on to the next משנה: Mishna, אין פודין
לא בעבדים ולא בשטרות ולא בקרקעות ולא בהקדשות. ein podin lo be'avadim
velo bishtarot velo bekarka'ot velo behekdeshot. You cannot redeem מעשר—excuse me, not
מעשר, you cannot do פדיון הבן pidyon haben, with עבדים, avadim, you
can't give your slave for פדיון הבן, pidyon haben. must be an
expensive slave if it's only worth five שקל. shekel. ולא בשטרות, velo
bishtarot, or with a שטר. shtar. Now the simple sense here of
a שטר shtar is that I have—Charlie owes me let's say ten
שקל, shekel, okay, and I have a document that proves that. But
because we're all afraid whether Charlie is ever going to pay up
and it's going to take whatever, the going value of this ten
שקל shekel debt is five שקל. shekel. Okay, I can't give the
כהן kohen my—that ten שקל shekel debt, ten שקל שטר, ten shekel
shtar, you know, to the כהן kohen because its market value is
five שקל. shekel. I can't give it to him, okay? ולא בשטרות,
velo bishtarot, that doesn't count. ולא בקרקעות, velo bekarka'ot, I can't even
give him a piece of land. Really, Greasly?
Yeah. ולא בהקדשות, velo behekdeshot, and not with things that are sanctified.
Now the גמרא's Gemara going to say obviously I don't own things
that are sanctified, we'll talk about that. כתב לכהן שחייב ליתן חמש
סלעים. katav lachohen shechayav liten chamesh sela'im. Now let's say not that
I give the
כהן kohen my Charlie's IOU to me, but I go to the
כהן kohen and I say, "Okay, I owe you five שקל shekel
here. I hereby owe כהן kohen so-and-so, you know, John Cohen five
שקל," shekel, and I sign it and עדים edim sign it and
I hand it to him. Now, does that count as if I've
paid him
the five שקל? shekel? No. So it says, חייב ליתן לו, chayav
liten lo, I still have to pay him the five שקל, shekel,
ובנו אינו פדוי. uveno eino faduy. Not only that, I have to
pay him because now I said I owe him five שקל, shekel,
so now I have this debt of five שקל shekel to him.
And once I pay that five שקל shekel debt, I still haven't
redeemed my son because now that five שקל shekel debt has been
in payment of this IOU. The IOU didn't count. The five שקל
shekel debt is in payment to the IOU and I haven't done
a פדיון הבן. pidyon haben, Now the גמרא's Gemara. going to ask
why not when I actually pay the five שקל shekel within the
context of the פדיון הבן, pidyon haben. let at least the five
שקל shekel when I pay up the money be that, and we'll
see why in the גמרא, Gemara it has to—right, exactly, because it
will be confused with cases of actually having paid him with a
שטר. shtar. Therefore since the שטר shtar itself didn't count, even when
I pay him it's not going to count as a פדיון הבן.
pidyon haben.
לפיכך אם רצה הכהן ליתן לו במתנה רשאי. lefichach im ratza hakohen
liten lo bematanah rashai. Therefore the best you can do in that
case is that the כהן kohen can give you a gift. Now
what a gift means is that he can either give you back
the IOU or—or you pay him your five שקל shekel that you
owed him and then he gives it—and then he gives it back
and then you do it again. So if the כהן's kohen a
nice guy he can try to neutralize the fact that you just
gave yourself an IOU which isn't going to help you. But otherwise
the actual payment of that IOU will not count for the פדיון
הבן.
pidyon haben Does the כהן kohen give then—the הנאה hana'ah that I
get from you doing the פדיון pidyon is worth
five שקל, shekel,
don't forget it, you know,
that's an interesting question of בההיא הנאה be'hahi hana'ah which comes up
by קידושין. kiddushin. And it doesn't come up so much by other
things. So the scope of בהיא הנאה be-hi hana'ah is interesting, which
I'm not going to talk about now. All right, anyway, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this, המפריש פדיון בנו ואבד חייב באחריותו. ha-mafrish
pidyon beno ve-avad chayav be-achrayuta. Let's say you set aside five שקל
shekel here, and I'm going to give it to the כהן, kohen,
and then it got lost. Tough luck, it's not a פדיון הבן
pidyon haben, until the כהן kohen gets it. It's not like once
you designate the money, first of all, there's no קדושה to the
money, so there's like, obviously, you haven't done anything until you actually
have given the כהן kohen the five שקל. shekel. שנאמר, she-ne'emar, as
the פסוק pasuk says, והיה יהיה לך, ve-haya yihye lecha, this is
in the פסוק pasuk to אהרן, Aharon, it shall be for you,
the פדיון הבן, pidyon haben. ופדויו תפדה, u-fado tifteh, you shall redeem.
So when is it considered redeemed? When it's יהיה לך, yihye lecha,
when the כהן kohen gets it into their hands. Before that, you
have not done the act of פדיון הבן. Pidyon HaBen Let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara מתניתין דלא כרבי, matnitin de-lo ke-Rebbi,
our משנה, Mishna that excludes עבדים, avadim, שטרות, shtarot, and קרקע. karka.
These are, by the way, the classic things that are
excluded when we exclude things, and we'll see why in a minute.
But that is not like רבי. Rebbi. דתניא, de-tanya, we talk in
a ברייתא, Baraita, רבי אומר, Rebbi omer, בכל פודה בכור אדם, be-chol
podeh bechor adam, you can do פדיון בכור pidyon bechor with anything
חוץ משטרות. chutz mi-shtarot. The only exception is שטרות, shtarot, not the
שטר shtar in our משנה mishna like the IOU, but the fact
that you're transferring a debt, the fact that Charlie owes me ten
שקל, shekel, I give that over, or whatever, let's say five שקל.
shekel. I'm just giving more for an example that it's worth less
than the face value. But anyway, I transfer that debt over to
the כהן. kohen. That's the one exception. מאי טעמא דרבי, mai ta'ama
de-Rebbi, what's the reason of רבי Rebbi that he only excludes שטרות?
shtarot? דריש ריבוי מיעוט וריבוי. darish ribui miyut u-ribui. So remember, we
had two possible ways of darshing פסוקים, psukim כלל פרט וכלל, klal
prat u-klal, which is general,
specific, general. כלל פרט וכלל klal prat u-klal is the end result
of that is that you only including things that are similar to
the פרט. prat. The concept is that the פרט prat is not
considered to be, it is considered to be the explanation of the
כלל. klal. With anything you want, get me anything, like I said
what do you want for lunch? I'll have anything, chicken. So the
chicken is not an example there, it's assumed to be the exact
application of the principle. So since by the time you get to
the פרט prat it's the only thing you mean, when you have
a later כלל klal you're only broadening the פרט. prat. So the
כלל פרט וכלל klal prat u-klal results with a broadening of the
פרט. prat. ריבוי מיעוט וריבוי ribui miyut u-ribui says that even when
you say the specific you're only, you don't mean specifically that thing.
You're only meaning to limit the very broad general statement. So by
the time you get to the second broad statement, then it's really
almost completely inclusive. The only thing that's excluded is something that is
completely dissimilar to the specific thing that is mentioned. Okay, so כלל
פרט וכלל klal prat u-klal has to be similar to the
specific. ריבוי מיעוט וריבוי, ribui miyut u-ribui, it just as long as
it is not completely dissimilar. So let's see for you. There are
different schools, okay? Although the גמרא Gemara will actually say that sometimes
you can switch schools, okay? So let's take a look. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this, דרבי דריש ריבוי מיעוט וריבוי דכתיב ופדויו
מבן חודש תפדה ריבה. de-Rebbi darish ribui miyut u-ribui de-chtiv u-fduyav miben
chodesh tifdeh riba.
So you can redeem him, you shall redeem, that's a broad statement.
It's all
inclusive. בערכך כסף חמשת שקלים מיעט. be-erkecha kesef chamesh shekalim mi'et. That's
a limiting, not a פרט. prat. Not only that, but limiting. So
כסף is the keyword here. כסף limits, so it has to be,
it can't be anything, it has to be somewhat like כסף. תפדה,
tifdeh, and then it says now תפדה tifdeh is actually written twice.
By it says,
I don't have a חומש Chumash here. But anyway, okay,
but it says תפדה tifdeh actually twice which is separating them to
make a ריבוי מיעוט וריבוי. ribui miyut u-ribui. So it says תפדה
tifdeh actually twice, ופדויו תפדה
ריבה, מיעט וריבה. u-fduyav tifdeh riba, mi'et ve-riba. So it's broad, narrow,
and broad. ריבה הכל, riba ha-kol, it includes everything, מאי ריבי ריבי
כל מילי, mai ribi ribi kol mili, it'll include absolutely everything. מאי
מיעט, mai mi'et, so in the end, what does it exclude? מיעט
שטרות. mi'et shtarot. It only excludes שטרות. shtarot. שטרות shtarot are most
dissimilar because שטרות shtarot do not have intrinsic value. Everything else has
intrinsic value, right? עבד, eved, קרקע, karka, everything has intrinsic value. The
only thing that doesn't is a שטר. shtar. It has a market
price, but its value is not intrinsic. Its value is only because
it can be used to collect other money. So there's no intrinsic
value in that. So that's the only thing that's excluded according to
that דרשה. drasha ורבנן דרשי כללי ופרטי וכללי. ve-Rabbanan darshi klalei u-pratei
ve-klalei. The רבנן Rabbanan do a כלל ופרט, klal u-prat, which is
going to be narrower. ופדויו מבן חודש כלל, u-fduyav miben chodesh klal,
בערכך כסף חמשת שקלים פרט, be-erkecha kesef chamesh shekalim prat, תפדה חזר
וכלל. tifdeh chazar ve-chalal. So the same פסוקים except we say כלל
פרט וכלל. klal prat u-klal. כלל פרט וכלל אי אתה דן אלא
כעין הפרט. klal prat u-klal ee ata dan ela ke-ein ha-prat. It
has to be similar to the specific. What was the
specific? Silver. מה הפרט מפורש דבר המיטלטל וגופו ממון. ma ha-prat meforash
davar ha-metaltel ve-gufo mamon. So what is specific about silver? It is
one, chattel, it is movable, and its intrinsic value. אף כל דבר
המיטלטל וגופו ממון, af kol davar ha-metaltel ve-gufo mamon, including, so therefore
only things that are like silver, that they are
chattel and that they are intrinsic value. יצאו כל דבר שאין מיטלטלין,
yatzu kol davar she-ein metaltelin, excludes קרקע karka which is not chattel,
is real
property. יצאו עבדים שהוקשו לקרקעות, yatzu avadim she-hukshu le-karka'ot, עבדים avadim always
go together with land. Interesting question about why, but let's say at
least one reason is because standard slaves would be used in the
field, so they would be considered sort of associated with the land.
There are other reasons as well, but anyway, slaves are always connected
to the land. So those are excluded because of the emphasis on
chattel and שטרות שאף על פי שהם מטלטלין אין גופן ממון shtarot
she'af al pi she'hem mitaltelin ein gufan mamon and שטרות shtarot are
excluded because although they are chattel, they don't have intrinsic value. So
anyway, these are the two approaches. If it has to be anything
similar to silver, we exclude things that are not chattel and not
intrinsic value, but if everything except that which is completely dissimilar, then
we only exclude שטרות. shtarot. One second. I do want to say
that this raises interesting questions about whether you can pay פדיון הבן
Pidyon HaBen? with cash. Because is cash considered to be a שטר?
shtar? Certainly a check is a שטר. shtar. If I write the
כהן Kohen a check, that's totally a שטר. shtar. That allows you
to present it to the bank to get money. Usually cash used
to be a type of a שטר shtar because it would allow
you in principle to get gold, right, when we were on the
gold
standard.
And then later silver. Really?
Okay, and then later silver. Now it really doesn't have any, it's
not that it can be exchanged for something else, right, that would
mean אין גופו ממון, ein gufo mamon, but it only has value
because we sort of give it value, you know, in society we
give it value. So is that considered to be non-intrinsic value? That
raises a very interesting question. There's a lot of, I mean what
does intrinsic value mean? Like if somebody draws a few squiggles on
a piece of paper, but he's an artist, you know, he's Picasso,
whatever, you know, so then that's what he would do instead of
paying his bar tab, you know, he would draw a few squiggles
on a piece of paper. So because you know, so is that
intrinsic value? So so that raises interesting questions whether cash nowadays is
considered גופו ממון gufo mamon and can you use it for something
like פדיון הבן? pidyon haben. Yes, there's definitely people say you can't.
But it would be very little,
it would be very little to do that. You know, if I
gave you silver, you'd have to go
to find out how
much silver's worth this amount of cash.
You know what I mean? It's kind of ironic.
Yes, it is, that is a good point.
Less usable but more intrinsic value. Yes.
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael in that ברייתא Baraita we read every morning,
פתח אליהו, Patach Eliyahu, right. And I remember
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva statement he used, ריבוי ומיעוט.
Ribuy U'miyut. Yes, that ברייתא, Baraita, that's true, and there are different
schools, that ברייתא, Baraita, the irony is it's appended to the ספרא,
Sifra, the beginning of the ספרא, Sifra, which is the רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva school.
Yeah, that's what I was going to ask.
There are different schools.
Do we follow רבי עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva? Is he with another תנא?
Tanna?
We, I don't know if there's a usually about that. It is
true that most of the תנאים are from the רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva school, but as we're about to see, the גמרא Gemara is
going to question how consistent we are with the usage of the
דרשה. So let's take a look. So the גמרא gemara says, okay,
so somebody can't give a coin or a silver mine because that'd
be קרקע, karka, right?
No. אמר ליה רבינא, Amlei Ravina, so אמר ליה רבינא לרב מרמר,
Amlei Ravina le-Maremar, ורבי ריבוי ומיעוט דרשי? ve-Rabbi Ribuy U'miyut darshi? So
רבינא Ravina said to מרמר, Maremar, does
רבי Rabbi
really of the school of ריבוי ומיעוט? Ribuy U'miyut? ורבי
כלל ופרט דרשי. ve-Rabbi Klal U'Prat darshi. You
see, here the גמרא Gemara is asking consistency. He's of the כלל
ופרט Klal U'Prat school. How do we know? דתניא, de-tanya, whatever, במרצע,
be-martzea, דתניא, de-tanya, מרצע, martzea, this is the awl that's used for
the hole in the ear of the slave, right, who wants to
stay for the, to stay with the master. אין לי אלא מרצע
מניין לרבות הסול והסירה והמחט והמקדח? ein li ela martzea minayin lerabot
hasol ve-hasira ve-hamachat ve-hamiktach? How do I know to include the, I
don't know, the thorn and the pick and the, you know, והמקדח
ve-hamiktach and the needle and the and the pen, that you can
use any pointy thing to make a hole? תלמוד לומר ולקחת לרבות
כל דבר שינקח ביד. Talmud lomar ve-lakachta lerabot kol davar shenikach bayad.
That you anything, so it's like a, anything that's taken, that that,
דברי רבי יאשיה ברבי יהודה. divrei Rabbi Yoshi be-Rabbi Yehuda. רבי אומר,
Rabbi omer, so that's one דרשה. רבי Rabbi says מרצע, martzea, מה
מרצע מיוחד של מתכת אף כל של מתכת. ma martzea meyuchad shel
matechet af kol shel matechet. It has to be like a מרצע
martzea that has to be a metal pointy thing, not anything. ואמרינן
במאי קמיפלגי? ve-amrinan be-mai kamifligi? Now, of course it's not clear there
that it's כלל ופרט Klal U'Prat or כלל, Klal, you don't see
where's the other broadening פסוק pasuk or whatever, but in another סוגיא
sugya we flesh it out and we say what are they debating?
רבי דריש כלל ופרט רבי יאשיה ברבי יהודה דריש ריבוי ומיעוט. Rabbi
darish Klal U'Prat Rabbi Yoshi be-Rabbi Yehuda darish Ribuy U'miyut. רבי Rabbi
does כלל ופרט, Klal U'Prat, רבי יאשיה ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yoshi be-Rabbi
Yehuda says ריבוי ומיעוט. Ribuy U'miyut. So רבי Rabbi that does כלל
ופרט Klal U'Prat is more narrow, it has to be like a
מרצע, martzea, it has to be metal. If you do ריבוי ומיעוט
Ribuy U'miyut it's broader and it can be anything that is movable.
The only thing that's excluded is if it's not done through a
movable pointy thing would either be let's say something that's connected to
the ground, like you have I don't know a post in the
ground with a point with a needle out of it or something
like that, or if you use let's say some type of a
of acid to burn a hole. That would be excluded. That's if
you're ריבוי ומיעוט, Ribuy U'miyut, you're very very broad. But רבי Rabbi
is כלל ופרט, Klal U'Prat, he's narrow, so it has to be
only something that's metal. So you see רבי Rabbi is of the
כלל ופרט Klal U'Prat school. So the גמרא Gemara says, רבי דריש
כלל ופרט רבי יאשיה ברבי יהודה דריש ריבוי ומיעוט. Rabbi darish Klal
U'Prat Rabbi Yoshi be-Rabbi Yehuda darish Ribuy U'miyut. It is, you're right,
בעלמא רבי כלל ופרט דריש. be-alma Rabbi Klal U'Prat darish. Really he's
generally of the כלל ופרט Klal U'Prat school. והכא כדתניא דבי רבי
ישמעאל, ve-hacha keditanya devei Rabbi Yishmael, like we've done דבי רבי ישמעאל,
devei Rabbi Yishmael, דתניא דבי רבי ישמעאל, de-tanya devei Rabbi Yishmael, רבי
ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael who normally goes by, surely, כלל ופרט, Klal U'Prat,
he himself has the דרשה, במים במים שתי פעמים. bamayim bamayim shtei
pe'amim. It says water twice, this is about the kosher
fish. אין זה כלל ופרט אלא ריבוי ומיעוט. ein ze Klal U'Prat
ela Ribuy U'miyut. The fact that it has the general statements juxtaposed,
not... hem":* הטל פרט ביניהם. hatel prat beineihem. *Refining "V'donam b'clall u'prat":*
ודונם בכלל ופרט. v'donam b'clall u'prat. *Refining "B'clall u'prat":* בכלל ופרט. b'clall
u'prat. *Refining "B'hekdeshot":* בהקדשות. b'hekdeshot. *Refining "Bechol elu":* בכל אלו. bechol elu.
*Refining "L'kohen":* לכהן. l'kohen. *Refining "Shehu chayav":* שהוא חייב. shehu chayav. *Refining
"Chamisha sela'im":* חמישה סלעים. chamisha sela'im. *Refining "Chayav litein lo":* חייב ליתן
לו. chayav litein lo. *Refining "Devar Torah":* דבר תורה. devar Torah. *Refining
"Beno paduy":* בנו פדוי. beno paduy. *Refining "L'chishiyitein":* לכשינתן. l'chishiyitein. *Refining "Gufo
mamon":* גופו ממון. gufo mamon. *Refining "Mai ta'ama":* מאי טעמא. mai ta'ama.
*Refining "Ein beno paduy":* אין בנו פדוי. ein beno paduy. *Refining "Gezeira
shema yomru":* גזירה שמא יאמרו. gezeira shema yomru. *Refining "Podim b'shtar":* פודים
בשטר. podim b'shtar. *Refining "Tani tana kamei d'Rav Nachman":* תני תנא קמיה
דרב נחמן. tani tana kamei d'Rav Nachman. *Refining "Beno paduy l'chishiyitein":* בנו
פדוי לכשינתן. beno paduy l'chishiyitein. *Refining "Zu divrei Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda
stima'ah":* זו דברי רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה סתימאה. zu divrei Rabbi Yose
b'Rabbi Yehuda stima'ah. *Refining "V'amrei lah zu divrei Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon
stima'ah":* ואמרי לה זו דברי רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון סתימאה. v'amrei lah
zu divrei Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon stima'ah. *Refining "Aval chachamim omrim":* אבל
חכמים אומרים. aval chachamim omrim. *Refining "Ein beno paduy":* אין בנו פדוי.
ein beno paduy. *Refining "V'hilchata ein beno
paduy":* והלכתא אין בנו פדוי. v'hilchata ein beno paduy. *Refining "Ked'amrinan b'maarava":*
כדאמרינן במערבא. ked'amrinan b'maarava. *Refining "Kol makom she'ata motzei shtei clallot hasmuchim
zeh lazeh":* כל מקום שאתה מוצא שתי כללות הסמוכים זה לזה. kol
makom she'ata motzei shtei clallot hasmuchim zeh lazeh. *Refining "Hatel prat beineihem":*
הטל פרט ביניהם. hatel prat beineihem. *Refining "V'donam b'clall u'prat":* ודונם בכלל
ופרט. v'donam b'clall u'prat. *Refining "B'clall u'prat":* בכלל ופרט. b'clall u'prat. *Refining
"B'hekdeshot":* בהקדשות. b'hekdeshot. *Refining "Bechol elu":* בכל אלו. bechol elu. *Refining "L'kohen":*
לכהן. l'kohen. *Refining "Shehu chayav":* שהוא חייב. shehu chayav. *Refining "Chamisha sela'im":*
חמישה סלעים. chamisha sela'im. *Refining "Chayav litein lo":* חייב ליתן לו. chayav
litein lo. *Refining "Devar Torah":* דבר תורה. devar Torah. *Refining "Beno paduy":*
בנו פדוי. beno paduy. *Refining "L'chishiyitein":* לכשינתן. l'chishiyitein. *Refining "Gufo mamon":* גופו
ממון. gufo mamon. *Refining "Mai ta'ama":* מאי טעמא. mai ta'ama. *Refining "Ein
beno paduy":* אין בנו פדוי. ein beno paduy. *Refining "Gezeira shema yomru":*
גזירה שמא יאמרו. gezeira shema yomru. *Refining "Podim b'shtar":* פודים בשטר. podim
b'shtar. *Refining "Tani tana kamei d'Rav Nachman":* תני תנא קמיה
דרב נחמן. tani tana kamei d'Rav Nachman. *Refining "Beno paduy l'chishiyitein":* בנו
פדוי לכשינתן.
beno paduy l'chishiyitein. *Refining "Zu divrei Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda stima'ah":* זו
דברי רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה סתימאה. zu divrei Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda
stima'ah.
*Refining "V'amrei lah zu divrei Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon stima'ah":* ואמרי לה
זו דברי רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון סתימאה. v'amrei lah zu divrei Rabbi
Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon stima'ah. *Refining "Aval chachamim omrim":* אבל חכמים אומרים. aval
chachamim omrim. *Refining "Ein beno paduy":* אין בנו פדוי. ein beno paduy.
*Refining "V'hilchata ein beno paduy":* והלכתא אין בנו פדוי. v'hilchata ein beno
paduy. *Refining "Ked'amrinan b'maarava":* כדאמרינן במערבא. ked'amrinan b'maarava. *Refining "Kol makom she'ata
motzei shtei clallot hasmuchim zeh lazeh":* כל מקום
שאתה מוצא שתי כללות הסמוכים זה לזה.
kol makom she'ata motzei shtei
clallot hasmuchim zeh lazeh.
*Refining "Hatel prat beineihem":* הטל פרט ביניהם. hatel prat beineihem. *Refining "V'donam
b'clall u'prat":* ודונם בכלל ופרט. v'donam b'clall u'prat. *Refining "B'clall u'prat":* בכלל
ופרט. b'clall u'prat. *Refining "B'hekdeshot":* בהקדשות. b'hekdeshot. *Refining "Bechol elu":* בכל אלו.
bechol elu. *Refining "L'kohen":* לכהן. l'kohen. *Refining "Shehu chayav":* שהוא חייב. shehu
chayav. *Refining "Chamisha sela'im":* חמישה סלעים. chamisha sela'im.
*Refining "Chayav litein lo":* חייב ליתן לו. chayav litein lo. *Refining "Devar
Torah":* דבר תורה. devar Torah. *Refining "Beno paduy":* בנו פדוי. beno paduy.
*Refining "L'chishiyitein":* לכשינתן. l'chishiyitein. *Refining "Gufo mamon":*
גופו ממון. gufo mamon. *Refining "Mai ta'ama":* מאי טעמא. mai ta'ama. *Refining
"Ein beno paduy":*
אין בנו פדוי. ein beno paduy. *Refining
"Gezeira shema yomru":* גזירה שמא יאמרו. gezeira shema yomru. *Refining "Podim b'shtar":*
פודים בשטר. podim b'shtar. *Refining "Tani tana kamei d'Rav Nachman":* תני תנא
קמיה דרב נחמן. tani tana kamei d'Rav Nachman. *Refining "Beno paduy l'chishiyitein":*
בנו פדוי לכשינתן. beno paduy l'chishiyitein. *Refining "Zu divrei Rabbi
Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda stima'ah":* זו דברי רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה סתימאה. zu
divrei Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda stima'ah. *Refining "V'amrei lah zu divrei Rabbi
Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon stima'ah":* ואמרי לה זו דברי רבי אלעזר ברבי שמע
Same thing, same thing, it's not גופו ממון. gufo mamon No, because
a
money, it's
endorsed though, it's not
like an IOU, that's actually
worth something. The bank, a
bank check, it's the same
thing.
I think
still it's a thing that you can go ahead to present in
order to collect. It's not the thing itself that's of interest. Right,
the real idea of אין גופו ממון, ein gufo mamon, and this
is again going back to the question of cash, is אין גופו
ממון ein gufo mamon is this itself is not really what you
care about. You really care about the thing that it's going to
let you get at, okay? That's אין גופו ממון, ein gufo mamon,
right? As opposed to like the example I gave, like a piece
of artwork, of course you care about that. Whatever bizarre reason you
assign this a million dollar value, you care about this. Cash, you
care about it, right? You want the cash. It's not like it's
standing in to allow you to get to something else that you
want. So that's the question about whether nowadays our cash is considered
גופו ממון or not.
Yes, yes. I'll owe you five shekel for the פדיון הבן. pidyon
haben Yeah. So then the פדיון הבן pidyon haben, then is honestly
based in...
Why doesn't it work? Yeah, so that's what we're saying. It could
be that it works מעיקר הדין, me'ikar hadin, and there is one
opinion that it does work. But we're saying that it does not
work because people will think
that the check itself was the פדיון הבן, pidyon haben, and that
will be misleading. Others say that תוספות Tosafot even raised the possibility
that it's not just appearance, that if you wrote the check, because
that didn't work for פדיון הבן, pidyon haben. now when you're paying
him, you're just paying him because he's got a check against you.
So you can't call that a פדיון הבן. pidyon haben Now you're
paying him because you owe him the five shekel.
I understand
it was nice what you intended to do, so the משנה mishna
says if he's a nice guy he'll help you out, but even
if you intended to do it, you didn't succeed. You actually wrote
him a check which didn't work, and now he's got a check
against you. So either when he collects the check it can't be
פדיון הבן pidyon haben altogether because he's just collecting the check. That's
not discussed in our גמרא Gemara but that's a possibility. Or it
might work that you, it does, it should work, but there's an
appearance concern. Yes?
What's beautiful about this is something about how nobody anticipated that in
today's world, had checks everything been fine, the whole ceremony of a
פדיון הבן pidyon haben. would have been, you
know,
diminished, because we'd just have written a check. Although people probably would
have tried to ritualize it anyway, but that's a good point, right?
Yeah, with all those coins. Right, right.
And it certainly doesn't have to be five separate coins or whatever,
it can be anything of intrinsic value. I want to talk about
what you know some practical things in a minute.
Can the כהן kohen override this by saying, you know, my question...
That what? Give me a check and I'll consider it that you
paid?
That's sort of what Michael was saying. No, because he has to
actually receive something of intrinsic
value. So that's really... yeah. But I want to talk about that
in a minute. Let's try to get a little bit further. Okay,
not exactly. If you give me some time I will talk about
that. לפיכך אם רצה כהן להחזירו לו
מתנה רשאי. lefikach im ratza kohen lehachaziro lo matana rashai. If the
כהן kohen is a nice guy, once he gets the check he'll
give him back the check or he'll give him the five shekel
payments back after he got the payment and then reuse them again.
Now we get to a very interesting discussion. תנינא להא דתנו רבנן.
tanina lehada de-tannu rabbanan. We taught in our משנה mishna, what we
taught in...
the Rabbis taught. תנו רבנן, tanu rabbanan, להא דתנו רבנן. lehada de-tannu
rabbanan. נתנו לעשרה כהנים בבת אחת. natnu le-asar kohanim bevas achas. Let's
say you gave your five shekel to ten כהנים kohanim at the
same time. There are ten כהנים kohanim in the room and you
basically says here it is, split it. Or רש"י says even more
radically you put it on the table and you walked away, you
guys figure it out. Okay, that's surprising that that counts as an
act of giving, the fact that you, I don't know, anyway,
יצא, yatzah, בזה אחר זה יצא, bezeh achar zeh yatzah, let's say
you gave to them, meaning you gave each one... five of them
one shekel each, that also works. Okay? You don't have to give
all five to one כהן, kohen, which is also interesting, right? Again,
this is the question of is it a debt or is it
an act of giving? If it's an act of giving you would
think you would have to do it with one person, give the
whole five shekel, not five different people, right? But if it's just
a debt, so fine, כהנים kohanim as a class got five shekel.
Okay, but of course if it's a formal act of giving, the
whole fact that we restrict it and say, and this goes to
the questions being asked, that you can't use a שטר, shtar, you
can't use קרקע, karka, that seems to formalize it and ritualize it
as an act. If it were just a debt, nobody would ever
say I can't pay a debt with land. The classic way debts
were paid were with land, right? So it seems on the one
hand it has these ritual requirements, it has to be only certain
types of objects, but we've been learning for the last few days
that it's all hinging on the כהן's kohen ability to sue and
the civil liability is what it hinges on. And now we're discussing
certain things which one would sort of question whether they're considered, you
know, in terms of a ritual act and we're saying that they're
okay. But now we get to the real fascinating one which is
the following.
One minute.
נטלו והחזירו לו יצא. natlo vehachaziro lo yatzah. If you gave it
to the כהן kohen and then he said, "Ah, you know what,
you're a nice guy, here I want to give you back a
gift," and he gave it back to you, you're יוצא. yotzei. So
that's you know, so that's sort of in the משנה, mishna although
not really because the משנה mishna might have been giving back the
payment of the check so that then you could give it back,
but it's hard to... it's not clear what the משנה mishna meant.
The משנה Mishnah. might mean you pay the check and then when
you do the פדיון הבן. Pidyon Haben You give him the פדיון
הבן Pidyon Haben money and he gives it back to you. So
it seems like that's how the גמרא Gemara is reading the משנה.
Mishna You have the check against you, you pay the check, now
you gave him the פדיון הבן Pidyon Haben money and he gave
it back as a gift. So giving the פדיון הבן Pidyon Haben,
money back as a gift works. And now we have an interesting
story, וכן היה מנהגו של רבי טרפון, vechen haya minhago shel Rabbi
Tarfon, and this was the practice of Rabbi Tarfon, שהיה נוטל ומחזיר.
shehaya notel umachzir.
He was a כהן, Kohein, he would take the money and then
he would then give it back as a gift. וכן שמעו חכמים
בדבר, vechen sham'u chachamim badavar, this is I think what normally happens
in פדיון הבן, Pidyon Haben the כהן Kohein takes the money and
gives it back, yeah, but he's entitled to keep it. וכששמעו חכמים
בדבר, ukshesham'u chachamim badavar, when the Rabbis heard about this, אמרו, amru,
they said, קיים זה הלכה זו. kiyam zeh halacha zu. Oh, he
fulfilled this idea about taking the, you know, this exact example of
taking the money and giving it back. So it sounds like it's
a good thing apparently, but we'll see in a minute. So the
גמרא Gemara says, הלכה זו ותו לא? halacha zu vetu lo? That's
the only הלכה halacha. Rabbi Tarfon fulfilled? אלא קיים זו אף הלכה
זו. ela kiyam zu af halacha zu. Rabbi Tarfon even fulfilled this
הלכה, this idea, the הלכה. I don't know, that said that it
works and it demonstrates that it works. Also he's being nice to
the fathers that maybe they don't have the money. So they're saying,
look what a good צדיק tzaddik he is, he does the מצוה
mitzvah פדיון הבן Pidyon Haben. and he gives it back to the
father.
Everything's exactly like what she said, God, I know.
Anyway, רבי חנינא הוי רגיל. Rabbi Chanina havei ragil. Now we have
one last story that's a little bit of a maybe leaves a
question mark about this. רבי חנינא הוי רגיל ושקיל, Rabbi Chanina havei
ragil veshakil, he would regularly take, ומהדר, umahader, he'd take the money
and then he'd give it back like we heard that Rabbi Tarfon
did. חזייה לההוא גברא דהוה קא אזיל ואתי קמיה. chazyei lehahu gavra
dehavei ka azil va'ati kamei. Now he once a person gave him
the five שקל, shekel, and then it's not clear, maybe he didn't
give it back right away. And then this person who had given
him the five שקל shekel was kept on walking in front of
him, walking back and forth. Right, waiting, hoping to get his five
שקל shekel back. So אמר ליה, amar lei, he said to him,
לא גמרת ויהבת. lo gamarta veyahavta. Now there's a question where to
put the קמי kami here, תוספות Tosafot has a couple possibilities. Anyway,
לא גמרת ויהבת. lo gamarta veyahavta. You did not give with a
full intent. You only gave because you were expecting to get it
back. You didn't give with a full desire to give it. מידם
ביש, midam bish, you did a bad thing, or לא יהבת מידם
ביש, lo yahavta midam bish, you didn't give anything, ביש, bish, you
did a bad
thing. הלכך אין בנו פדוי. hilkach ein bno paduy. Therefore, if you
didn't give it with גמירות דעת, gmirot da'at, then the that it
does not work. Now, does that mean, what does exactly does that
mean? Does that mean that you can't give it back? I mean
the גמרא Gemara said explicitly you can give it back. It means
that if you in a certain context where it's clear that you're
giving it back, then you, I mean in a certain context where
it's known the כהן Kohein gives it back and you don't do
with full דעת da'at that he can keep it, then it doesn't
work. Now this raises a couple of interesting questions. First of all,
this גמרא Gemara frames it as the כהן Kohein of his own
will chose to give it back. There's another גמרא Gemara in קידושין
Kiddushin that speaks about the whole principle of מתנה על מנת להחזיר.
matanah al menat lehachzir. That if you give something as a gift
with an explicit condition that it be returned, that actually works under
certain circumstances. I mean not for payment of debt obviously, but certain
acts that are more about like, you know, technical ownership, like you
give your לולב על מנת להחזיר. lulav al menat lehachzir. And one
example that it gives is פדיון הבן. pidyon haben. You give the
כהן Kohein the five שקל על מנת להחזיר, shekel al menat lehachzir,
that it actually works. Now the question then is, obviously the question
is, well if that works with explicit intent to get it back,
right, then why is this wrong? You know, with this isn't, you
know, so תוספות Tosafot sort of tries to navigate that, that there's
a difference between giving without really wanting to give or giving fully
but with a condition to give back. First of all, yeah, I
know. Anyway, first of all, so there's a problem about trying to
navigate the difference about those two cases. But the other question is
why the גמרא Gemara had to play all of these games about
like, you know, let's, I'm not going to say I'm doing it
and then after I give it back, I'm going to, you know,
why not just stipulate that it's על מנת להחזיר? al menat lehachzir?
And תוספות Tosafot gets into whole questions about whether, you know, although
the גמרא Gemara seemed to praise Rabbi Tarfon for doing this, about
whether this is actually appropriate. Does this not undermine the institution in
one of two ways? One way is, is if you're the כהן
Kohein that everybody is giving back to, then everybody
is going to go to you. And none of the other כהנים
Kohanim are going to get it and they want, they want the
money. Okay, number one. Number two is, is that even if that's
not a concern, the very fact that you're constantly giving it back,
does that somehow undermine the institution, the importance of this as a
sort of as a priestly gift that we're always just making a
game out of it? So תוספות Tosafot raises those questions both about
this גמרא Gemara here and why this גמרא Gemara, isn't framed as
the מתנה על מנת להחזיר. matanah al menat lehachzir. Now what I
want to say is,
I'm sorry, so I don't understand the answer then.
I didn't give you an answer, I just raised a couple of
questions. Okay, but we don't have time to work out the answers,
but what I'm raising is the issues. Number one is why is
the concern here different if מתנה על מנת להחזיר matanah al menat
lehachzir works? And number two is the גמרא Gemara here sort of
started by saying, oh it's great that Rabbi Tarfon does this. But
then it ends, it sort of left it with a question mark
because maybe if you do it too much people don't really do
it with גמירות דעת gmirot da'at and that leads תוספות Tosafot to
another question in general, is this appropriate or not? Does this undermine
the institution of מתנות כהונה matnot kehunah and steal it away from
other כהנים? Kohanim? So that's a range of questions about מתנה על
מנת להחזיר. matanah al menat lehachzir. But I now want to make
an important other point, which is the general question we've been. dealing
about the ritualized about is it a ritual or is it a
debt? If it's a ritual if it's a debt there's no way
you can pay a debt מתנה על מנת להחזיר matana al m'nat
lehachzir right? Yes so which might be by the way why this
גמרא Gemara does not talk about מתנה על מנת להחזיר. matana al
m'nat lehachzir. This גמרא, Gemara it's possible to say rejects מתנה על
מנת להחזיר. matana al m'nat lehachzir. This גמרא Gemara thinks that you
have to pay the debt. And if you did a מתנה על
מנת להחזיר matana al m'nat lehachzir it wouldn't work at all. Okay
and that's certainly this גמרא's Gemara constantly been talking about the debt
that underlies the obligation about פדיון הבן. pidyon haben But once you
introduce another גמרא Gemara in קידושין Kiddushin that talks about מתנה על
מנת להחזיר, matana al m'nat lehachzir, that becomes a lot of confusion.
Then you have to say maybe there are two things going on
here. You can do the act of פדיון הבן pidyon haben in
a formal ritual way, מתנה על מנת להחזיר, matana al m'nat lehachzir,
but then you haven't actually paid the debt and the debt itself
has to be paid. And then it raises an interesting question, which
is when our משנה Mishna. excludes things like קרקע, karka, it's probably
excluding it from the ritual act, but it isn't necessarily excluding it
from the aspect of the debt. So can you do the following?
Ready for this? Can you give five שקל shekel מתנה על מנת
להחזיר? matana al m'nat lehachzir? You get it back. You did the
ritual act, but you didn't pay the debt. And then for the
debt you give him five שקל shekel worth of קרקע, karka, right?
So that gets into a whole fascinating question of is there one
thing going on or two things? And I want to tell you
about a fascinating story, which I know about somebody who was like
had these crazy crazy חומרות. chumrot. So he didn't know how much
five שקל shekel was worth. Maybe it's worth thousands of dollars, who
knows what it's worth. So therefore, what he did was the following:
he gave the standard amount that's assumed to be the
five שקל, shekel, you know, whatever we said that was, a hundred
whatever, 19.2, what did we say? 96 grams, or whatever it was,
he gave that to the כהן kohen fine. And then he gave
him, like, you know, his wife's diamond ring and all this type
of stuff, מתנה על מנת להחזיר. matana al m'nat lehachzir.
So therefore, like you know, for the debt he's doing that and
for the other thing just in case it was worth a lot
more, he's doing it through the מתנה. matana. Anyway that raises this
question about is there one or two things? And our
גמרא Gemara does not at all acknowledge the מתנה על מנת להחזיר.
matana al m'nat lehachzir. Seems to be that it has to really
be a payment of debt. Yes, Bobby.
I think what's fascinating is that the גמרא Gemara. is looking at
intention.
Right, that's an excellent point and תוספות Tosafot said that. Who תוספות
Tosafot says whatever happened to דברים שבלב אינם דברים? devarim she'belev einam
devarim? Who cares if after the fact it looks like he didn't
have גמירת דעת? gemirat da'at? Normally, you know, any if the fact
that it wasn't explicit we all go by ההלכה halacha by just
what's observable. And it could so תוספות Tosafot says well maybe it
was very very obvious and da da and then even at the
time. But anyway, it's it is a very big question. And maybe
this just meant it as a, you know, רבנן-ically rabbanan he didn't
want to allow this to count, but you know, you know as
sort of like as a punishment, as a lesson. But תוספות Tosafot
raises exactly the question you raised. Yes.
Is there a distinction between the case of say the לולב lulav
where it's expressed by both parties and in the first case?
Well that's what תוספות Tosafot raises.
Right. So תוספות Tosafot says you can't say I'm giving you this
with the condition...
Well the גמרא Gemara in קידושין Kiddushin says you can say that,
but that's exactly what תוספות Tosafot deals with, is that this גמרא
Gemara maybe is if you say explicitly with this intent, maybe it's
better than to pretend to give it with גמירת דעת gemirat da'at
and not have גמירת דעת. gemirat da'at. If you don't say anything
and you give it and you're hoping you'll get it back, right,
that might be worse than just making it explicit and framing it
for both parties. But you could frame it for both parties. That's
the גמרא. Yes, there's a different גמרא that says that על מנת
להחזיר al m'nat lehachzir works. Yes, yes. But that's maybe as I
said, but maybe not for the debt part of it, maybe for
the ritual of giving it.
It raises the question doesn't it? What? What the whole thing is
about then.
That's what I said, there might be two aspects, the ritual and
the debt. I know that I know we're running out of time
but I think the rest will go quick so if people can
give me about three more minutes we can finish to the משנה.
mishnah. Okay. המפריש פדיון בנו ואבד חייב באחריותו. Hamaprish pidyon beno ve'avad
chayav be'achrayuto. If you set aside the five שקל shekel and it
gets lost then you have to pay because obviously it's until it
gets to the כהן. kohen. מנלן? Menalan? Where do we know this?
אמר ריש לקיש אתיא ערך ערך מערכין. Amar Reish Lakish atya erech
erech me'erchin. You learn it from ערכין Erchin because by ערכין Erchin
it says also ערך erech and by פדיון הבן pidyon haben it
says ערך חמשת שקלים. erech chameshet shekalim. And by ערכין Erchin we
know if you say I have to pay x amount for this
person that it's until you actually pay to the בית המקדש. Beit
HaMikdash. So somehow we already know that by ערכין. Erchin. רב דימי
אמר רבי יוחנן וכל בכור בניך תפדה ולא יראו פני ריקם. Rav
Dimi amar Rabbi Yochanan ve'chol bechor banecha tifdeh ve'lo yeira'u fanai reikam.
Redeem your firstborn and don't appear empty-handed. ויליף ריקם ריקם מעולת ראיה.
Veyalif reikam reikam me'olat re'iyah. So that's the verse that's used also
for appearing in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and bringing a קרבן
korban on the רגלים. regalim. And therefore we know that there obviously
if you don't bring a קרבן korban you say oh well I
separated the money for a קרבן korban but it got lost. Tough
so what? Don't appear empty-handed, right? You don't fulfill your קרבן korban
obligation unless you have the קרבן. korban. So the same way that
is true, you don't fulfill your קרבן korban obligation until you bring
it, you don't fulfill your פדיון הבן pidyon haben, obligation until you
give it. Okay. ויליף מה ריקם ריקם מעולת ראיה מה עולת ראיה
חייב באחריותו. Veyalif mah reikam reikam me'olat re'iyah mah olat re'iyah chayav
be'achrayuto. The same way there you're responsible for it until you bring
it and you don't fulfill it until you bring it, אף פדיון
הבן חייב באחריותו. af pidyon haben chayav be'achrayuto. Here too until you
giving it you do not fulfill. So מתקיף לה רב פפא קרא
לקרא, matkif lah Rav Papa kra lekra, who needs a פסוק pasuk?
for your פסוק? pasuk Meaning which means what? You have a פסוק
pasuk about פדיון הבן, pidyon haben why are you quoting these other
פסוקים about
עולת ראיה? olat re'iyah? Now why not? Because you need to prove
it, but because the פסוק pasuk. that proves it is already in
our משנה. mishnah Our משנה mishnah. quotes a different פסוק. pasuk Okay.
So אלא אמר רב פפא הכא כדקתני טעמא, ela amar Rav Papa
hacha k'detani ta'ama, the reason for the פדיון הבן pidyon haben, is
explicit in the משנה. mishnah. יהיה לך, yihiyeh lecha, it shall be
for you, אך פדה תפדה, ach padoh tifdeh, you redeem the firstborn.
So when is the firstborn redeemed? When יהיה לך, yihiyeh lecha, when
the כהן kohen gets the money. That is the פסוק of giving
the money to the כהן, kohen, so when you get the money,
that's when it's redeemed. That's the דרשה. That's what it says in
the משנה. mishnah. We don't need a דרשה for פדיון הבן, pidyon
haben it's in the משנה. mishnah. So וכי איתמר דריש לקיש ארישא
איתמר. vechi itmar de'Reish Lakish areisha itmar. So what were these דרשות
said to explain that we quoted? They were said for the beginning
of the משנה. mishnah, מת לאחר שלשים יום אף על פי שלא
נתן יתן. met l'achar shloshim yom af al pi shelo natan yiten.
If the son dies after thirty days, the father still has to
do a פדיון הבן pidyon haben? even though his son is dead.
Remember we discussed that before. מנלן, menalan, where do you know that?
אמר ריש לקיש אתיא ערך ערך מערכין. amar Reish Lakish atya erech
erech me'erachin. You learn it from ערכין. erachin. Now here actually you
learn something else. If somebody takes a vow to give money to
the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and he dies, that vow becomes a
debt and that debt gets passed down to the sons. So רש"י
says actually what we're asking is a similar question. Not just if
the son dies. Let's say both the son and the father die.
Okay? How do you know the other brothers have to pay the
debt of the פדיון הבן? pidyon haben That it becomes a debt
on the estate and it has to be paid even if the
people who were obligated in the משנה, both the son and the
father, have died? That's a good question. No, that you learn out
from ערכין. erachin. רב דימי אמר רבי יוחנן ובכל בכור בניך תפדה
ולא יראו פני ריקם. Rav Dimi amar Rabbi Yochanan u'v'chol bechor banecha
tifdeh v'lo yeira'u panay reikam. מה להלן יורשים חייבין. mah l'halan yorshim
chayavin. Interesting, if somebody is obligated to bring an עולה olah like
and he dies, his heirs have to bring it from the estate.
אף כאן יורשים חייבין, af kan yorshim chayavin, here too there is
a debt. This once again emphasizes the debt aspect of פדיון הבן
that even if the father and son are both dead, the debt
is still on the estate and it's not just this ritual aspect.
So everything we've been seeing basically says it starts as a debt,
there might be ritual aspects of how it's given, right? Not עבדים,
avadim, not קרקע, karka, but it's fundamentally at its root is this
debt and that really raises questions about מתנה מנת להחזיר, matana m'nat
lehachzir,
which is not in our גמרא at all. To think that that
can work is really quite quite shocking, and here we end with
the fact that if all the parties die, it still remains a
debt on the estate. Yeah.
So this means that I mean we've had generations who did not